In my previous life, I was an artist.
في حياتي السابقة كنت فناناً
I still paint. I love art.
ما زلت أرسم، أحب الفن
I love the joy that color can give to our lives
أحب تلك البهجة التي تضفيها الألوان في حياتنا
and to our communities,
و في مجتمعاتنا،
and I try to bring something of the artist in me
و أنا أحاول أن أقدم شيئاً من الفنان في داخلي
in my politics,
في سياستي
and I see
و أنا أرى
part of my job today, the reason for being here,
آن جزء من واجبي اليوم و سبب وجودي هنا
not just to campaign for my party,
ليس بداعي دعم حزبي
but for politics, and the role it can play
بل للسياسة و الدور الذي من الممكن ان تلعبه
for the better in our lives.
لتجعل حياتنا افضل
For 11 years, I was mayor of Tirana, our capital.
كنت مدير بلدية لعاصمتنا تيرانا لمدة ١١ سنه
We faced many challenges.
واجهتنا الكثير من التحديات
Art was part of the answer,
الفن كان جزء من الحل
and my name, in the very beginning,
و اسمي منذ البداية
was linked with two things:
كان مرتبطا مع شيئين:
demolition of illegal constructions
هدم المنشئات غير القانونية
in order to get public space back,
من اجل استرجاع الاراضي العامة
and use of colors in order to revive the hope
واستخدام الألوان من أجل إحياء الأمل
that had been lost in my city.
و الذي كان مفقودا في المدينة
But this use of colors was not just an artistic act.
لكن استخدام الالوان لم يكن فقط حركة فنية
Rather, it was a form of political action
بل كانت شكلا من أشكال العمل السياسي
in a context when the city budget I had available
في وقت كانت فيه الميزانية المتاحة للمدينه
after being elected amounted to zero comma something.
بعد انتخابي ، اكثر بقليل من الصفر
When we painted the first building,
بعدما طلينا أول بناء
by splashing a radiant orange on the somber gray
بعد تغيير اللون الرمادي الحزين إلى البرتقالي المشع
of a facade,
في الواجهة
something unimaginable happened.
حدث شيء من الصعب تصوره
There was a traffic jam
كان هناك ازدحام مروري
and a crowd of people gathered
و حشد من الناس
as if it were the location of some spectacular accident,
و كما لو كان هناك حادث دراماتيكي
or the sudden sighting of a visiting pop star.
او رؤية نجم بوب مشهور
The French E.U. official in charge of the funding
الفرنسي المسؤول عن التمويل المبعوث من الاتحاد الأوربي
rushed to block the painting.
هرع لمنع عملية الطلاء
He screeched that he would block the financing.
مهدداً بوقف التمويل
"But why?" I asked him.
سألته: لكن لماذا؟
"Because the colors you have ordered
رد قائلا: بأن الألوان التي طلبتها
do not meet European standards," he replied.
لا تستوفي المعايير الأوربية
"Well," I told him,
قلت: حسنا
"the surroundings do not meet European standards,
المناطق المحيطة لا تستوفي المعايير الأوربية
even though this is not what we want,
حتى و إن كان هذا ليس ما نريد
but we will choose the colors ourselves,
لكننا سنختار الألوان بأنفسنا
because this is exactly what we want.
لان هذا بالضبط ما نريد
And if you do not let us continue with our work,
و إذا لم تجعلنا نواصل عملنا
I will hold a press conference here,
سوف اعقد مؤتمر صحفي هنا
right now, right in this road,
الآن، هنا بهذا بالشارع
and we will tell people that you look to me
و سوف اخبر الناس أنكم تنظرون إلي
just like the censors of the socialist realism era."
تماما مثل الرقابة من عصر الواقعية الاشتراكية
Then he was kind of troubled,
بعد ذلك، بدا مضطربا بعض الشيء
and asked me for a compromise.
و طلب آن نتوصل إلى حل وسط
But I told him no, I'm sorry,
لكني قلت: لا، أنا آسف
compromise in colors is gray,
الحلول الوسطى في لغة الألوان هي اللون الرمادي
and we have enough gray to last us a lifetime.
و نحن لدينا من الرمادي ما يكفينا مدى الحياة
(Applause)
تصفيق
So it's time for change.
إذاً حان وقت التغيير
The rehabilitation of public spaces
إعادة تأهيل الأماكن العامة
revived the feeling of belonging
إحياء الشعور بالانتماء
to a city that people lost.
لمدينه أضاعها الناس
The pride of people about their own place of living,
فخر و اعتزاز الناس بمكان عيشهم
and there were feelings that had been buried
و كانت هناك مشاعر دفنت
deep for years under the fury of the illegal,
عميقا لسنين و الغضب بسبب
barbaric constructions that sprang up in the public space.
المنشآت الهمجية الغير مشروعه التي ظهرت في الأماكن العامة
And when colors came out everywhere,
عندما أصبحت الألوان في كل مكان
a mood of change started transforming the spirit of people.
جو من التغيير بدا بتغير روح الناس
Big noise raised up: "What is this? What is happening?
بدا الناس بالتساؤل: ما هذا؟ مالذي يحدث؟
What are colors doing to us?"
مالذي تفعله الألوان بنا؟
And we made a poll,
قمنا بعمل استفتاء
the most fascinating poll I've seen in my life.
و هو من أروع الاستفتاءات التي رايتها في حياتي
We asked people, "Do you want this action,
سألنا الناس: "هل تريد هذه الحركة،
and to have buildings painted like that?"
و أن تكون المباني مطليه بهذا الشكل؟"
And then the second question was,
و السؤال الثاني كان:
"Do you want it to stop or do you want it to continue?"
"هل تريد هذه الحركة أن تتوقف أو أن تستمر؟"
To the first question,
كان جواب السؤال الأول:
63 percent of people said yes, we like it.
63% من الناس قالوا نعم، تُعجبنا
Thirty-seven said no, we don't like it.
37% قالوا: لا، لا تُعجبنا
But to the second question, half of them that didn't like it,
لكن جواب السؤال الثاني، نصف الذين لم تعجبهم الحركة
they wanted it to continue. (Laughter)
أرادوا أن تستمر
So we noticed change.
لاحظنا أن هناك تغيير
People started to drop less litter in the streets, for example,
على سبيل المثال: لم يعد الناس برمي النفايات بالشارع كما بالسابق
started to pay taxes,
و بدؤوا بدفع الضرائب
started to feel something they had forgotten,
و بدؤوا يشعرون بأشياء كانوا قد نسوها
and beauty was acting as a guardsman
وكان الجمال يقوم بدور الحرس
where municipal police, or the state itself, were missing.
حيث كانت الشرطة المحلية ، أو الحكومية نفسها غير متواجدة
One day I remember walking along a street
أتذكر في يوم ما كنت امشي في احد الشوارع
that had just been colored,
التي كانت قد قمنا بطلائها قريبا
and where we were in the process of planting trees,
و التي كنا بصدد غرس الأشجار بها
when I saw a shopkeeper and his wife
رأيت صاحب محل و زوجته
putting a glass facade to their shop.
يقومان بتركيب واجهة زجاجية للمحل
They had thrown the old shutter
و ألقو باب المتجر القديم
in the garbage collection place.
في مكان جمع القمامة
"Why did you throw away the shutters?" I asked him.
سألتهما: لماذا ألقيتما باب المتجر؟
"Well, because the street is safer now," they answered.
أجابا: "لأن الشوارع أصبحت آمنة الآن"
"Safer? Why? They have posted more policemen here?"
"آمنة؟ لماذا؟ هل زاد عدد رجال الشرطة في المنطقة؟"
"Come on, man! What policemen?
"هيا يا رجل! أي رجال شرطة؟"
You can see it for yourself. There are colors,
يمكنك أن ترى بنفسك، هناك ألوان.
streetlights, new pavement with no potholes,
إضاءة بالشوارع، و رصيف جديد بلا حفر.
trees. So it's beautiful; it's safe."
أشجار. المكان جميل؛ و آمن."
And indeed, it was beauty that was giving people
و بالفعل، كان الجمال هو ما أعطى الناس
this feeling of being protected.
هذا الإحساس بأنهم محميون و آمنون
And this was not a misplaced feeling.
و هذا لم يكن مجرد إحساس
Crime did fall.
معدلات الجريمة انخفضت
The freedom that was won in 1990
الحرية التي نلناها عام 1990
brought about a state of anarchy in the city,
أحدثت نوعاً من الفوضى في المدينة
while the barbarism of the '90s
بينما همجية التسعينات
brought about a loss of hope for the city.
أحدثت نوعاً من فقدان الأمل في المدينة
The paint on the walls did not feed children,
الطلاء على الجدران لم يطعم الأطفال
nor did it tend the sick or educate the ignorant,
و لم يعالج المرضى أو يعلم الجاهل
but it gave hope and light,
و لكنه جلب الأمل و النور
and helped to make people see
و ساعد الناس لترى
there could be a different way of doing things,
انه هناك طرق أخرى لعمل الأشياء،
a different spirit, a different feel to our lives,
روح مختلفة، إحساس مختلف في حياتنا
and that if we brought the same energy and hope
و أننا إذا جلبنا نفس الأمل و الطاقة
to our politics, we could build a better life
للسياسة، يمكننا أن نبني حياة افضل
for each other and for our country.
لبعضنا البعض و للبلاد
We removed 123,000 tons of concrete
لقد قمنا بإزالة 123،000 طن من الخرسانة
only from the riverbanks.
من ضفاف النهر فقط
We demolished more than 5,000 illegal buildings
قمنا بهدم اكتر من 5000 مبنى غير مصرح به
all over the city,
في أرجاء المدينة
up to eight stories high, the tallest of them.
أعلى مبنى كان بارتفاع 8 طوابق
We planted 55,000 trees and bushes in the streets.
قمنا بغرس 55،000 شجرة و شجيرة في الشوارع
We established a green tax,
أسسنا ضريبة للتشجير
and then everybody accepted it
و كل الناس قبلت بها
and all businessmen paid it regularly.
و أصحاب الأعمال دفعوا بانتظام
By means of open competitions,
و بداعي المنافسة المفتوحة
we managed to recruit in our administration
استطعنا أن نجند في إدارتنا
many young people,
العديد من الشباب
and we thus managed to build
و استطعنا أن نبني
a de-politicized public institution
مؤسسة غير سياسية
where men and women were equally represented.
تمثل الرجال و النساء بمساواة.
International organizations
المنظمات العالمية
have invested a lot in Albania during these 20 years,
قد قامت باستثمار الكثير من الأموال في البانيا خلال العشرون سنة الماضية
not all of it well spent.
لم تنفق كلها بشكل سليم.
When I told the World Bank directors
عندما أخبرت مدراء البنك الدولي
that I wanted them to finance a project to build
أنني أريد تمويلاً لمشروع بناء
a model reception hall for citizens
صالة استقبال نموذجية للمواطنين
precisely in order to fight endemic daily corruption,
تحديداً لمحاربة الفساد اليومي المتوطن
they did not understand me.
لم يفهموا فكرتي
But people were waiting in long queues
و لكن الناس كانوا يقفون في طوابير طويلة
under sun and under rain
تحت الشمس و تحت المطر
in order to get a certificate or just a simple answer
ليحصلوا على شهادة رسمية أو مجرد إجابة بسيطة
from two tiny windows of two metal kiosks.
من شباكين صغيرين في كشكين حديديين
They were paying in order to skip the queue,
كانوا يدفعون الرشاوي ليتخطوا الطابور،
the long queue.
الطوابير الطويلة.
The reply to their requests was met
كانت طلباتهم تجاب
by a voice coming from this dark hole,
بواسطة صوت قادم من فتحة مظلمة،
and, on the other hand,
و في المقابل،
a mysterious hand coming out to take their documents
كانت يد غامضة تمتد لتأخذ مستنداتهم
while searching through old documents for the bribe.
بينما تبحث عن الرشوة وسط المستندات القديمة.
We could change the invisible clerks within the kiosks,
يمكننا أن تغير الكَتبة الخفيين داخل الأكشاك
every week, but we could not change this corrupt practice.
كل أسبوع، و لكننا لا نستطيع تغيير هذه الممارسة الفاسدة.
"I'm convinced," I told a German official
" أنا مقتنع،" أخبرت مسؤولا ألمانياً
with the World Bank,
مع البنك الدولي،
"that it would be impossible for them to be bribed
"أنه من المستحيل أن يرتشوا
if they worked in Germany,
إن كانوا يعملون في ألمانيا،
in a German administration,
تحت إدارة ألمانية،
just as I am convinced that if you put German officials
كما أني أيضا مقتنع أنه إذا وضعنا مسؤولين ألمان
from the German administration in those holes,
من الإدارة الألمانية في هذه الفتحات،
they would be bribed just the same."
فإنهم سوف يقبلون الرشاوي أيضا."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's not about genes.
المسألة ليست في الجينات
It's not about some being with a high conscience
و ليست مسألة أن البعض لديه ضمير واع
and some others having not a conscience.
و بعض الناس ليس لديهم ضمير
It's about system, it's about organization.
المسألة مسألة نظام ، مسألة تنظيم
It's also about environment and respect.
و أيضا مسألة بيئة و احترام.
We removed the kiosks.
قمنا بإزالة الأكشاك.
We built the bright new reception hall
و بنينا قاعة الاستقبال النيرة الجديدة
that made people, Tirana citizens,
جعلت الناس، مواطني تيرانا
think they had traveled abroad when they entered
يشعرون انهم قد سافروا خارج البلاد عندما يدخلون
to make their requests.
ليدلوا بطلباتهم
We created an online system of control
أنشانا نظام للتحكم على الإنترنت
and so speeded up all the processes.
و من ثم أصبحت الإجراءات اسرع
We put the citizen first, and not the clerks.
جعلنا المواطنين هم الأولوية، و ليس الكَتبة.
The corruption in the state administration
الفساد في إدارة الولاية
of countries like Albania --
في دول مثل البانيا--
it's not up to me to say also like Greece --
و ليس لي الحق أن أقول مثل اليونان أيضا--
can be fought only by modernization.
يمكن أن يحارب فقط بالتحديث.
Reinventing the government by reinventing politics itself
إعادة تشكيل الحكومة عن طريق إعادة تشكيل السياسة نفسها
is the answer, and not reinventing people
هذا هو الحل، و ليس إعادة تشكيل الناس
based on a ready-made formula
على أساس معادلة مكتوبه مسبقا
that the developed world often tries in vain to impose
يحاول العالم المتقدم، بلا جدوى ان يطبقها
to people like us.
على أناس أمثالنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Things have come to this point
وصلت الاشياء الى هذه المرحلة
because politicians in general,
لأن السياسيين بصورة عامة،
but especially in our countries, let's face it,
و خاصة في بلداننا، دعونا نواجهه اﻷمر،
think people are stupid.
يعتقدون أن الناس أغبياء
They take it for granted that, come what may,
يعتقدون انه من المسلمات، مهما كان،
people have to follow them,
يجب على الناس أن يتبعوهم،
while politics, more and more, fails to offer answers
في حين أن السياسات ، مرة تلو الأخرى، فشلت في تقديم إجابات
for their public concerns
لمخاوفهم العامة
or the exigencies of the common people.
أو مقتضيات عامة الناس.
Politics has come to resemble
السياسة أصبحت تمثل
a cynical team game played by politicians,
لعبة ساخرة يلعبها السياسيون،
while the public has been pushed aside
بينما يتم دفع الشعب جانباً
as if sitting on the seats of a stadium
كأنهم يجلسون على مقاعد في المدرج
in which passion for politics
حيث الشغف للسياسة
is gradually making room for blindness and desperation.
يتيح الفرصة تدريجيا للعمى و اليأس.
Seen from those stairs, all politicians today
و بالمراقبة من تلك المدرجات، كل السياسيون اليوم
seem the same,
يبدون متشابهين،
and politics has come to resemble
و أصبحت السياسة تمثل
a sport that inspires more aggressiveness
رياضة تحفز المزيد من العنف
and pessimism than social cohesion
و التشاؤم ، اكثر من التماسك الاجتماعي
and the desire for civic protaganism.
و الرغبة في دعم المدنية.
Barack Obama won
باراك أوباما فاز
— (Applause) —
—(تصفيق)—
because he mobilized people as never before
لأنه حرك الناس بشكل غير مسبوق
through the use of social networks.
من خلال استخدام الشبكات الاجتماعية.
He did not know each and every one of them,
فهو لم يعرف كل واحد فيهم،
but with an admirable ingenuity,
و لكنه ببراعة تثير الإعجاب
he managed to transform them into activists
استطاع أن يحولهم إلى ناشطين
by giving them all the possibility to hold in their hands
بإعطائهم جميع الإمكانيات بين أيديهم
the arguments and the instruments that each would need
و كل الحجج و الأدوات اللازمة التي يحتاجونها
to campaign in his name by making his own campaign.
لينظمو حملة بإسمه عن طريق عمل حملته الخاصة
I tweet. I love it.
غردت على تويتر. أحببتها.
I love it because it lets me get the message out,
أحببتها لأنه جعلني انشر الرسالة،
but it also lets people get their messages to me.
و لكنه أيضا يدع الناس يوصلون رسالتهم لي.
This is politics, not from top down,
هذه هي السياسة، ليس من الأعلى للأسفل،
but from the bottom up, and sideways,
و لكن من الأسفل للأعلي ، و بالجانبين
and allowing everybody's voice to be heard
و إتاحة أصوات الجميع لتسمع
is exactly what we need.
هو بالضبط ما نحتاجه
Politics is not just about leaders.
السياسة ليست فقط محصورة على القادة.
It's not just about politicians and laws.
و ليست محصورة على الساسة و القوانين
It is about how people think,
لكنها تمثل تفكير الناس،
how they view the world around them,
و كيف يرون العالم من حولهم،
how they use their time and their energy.
كيف يستخدمون وقتهم و طاقتهم.
When people say all politicians are the same,
عندما يقول الناس أن كل الساسة متشابهون
ask yourself if Obama was the same as Bush,
اسأل نفسك إن كان أوباما مثل بوش،
if François Hollande is the same as Sarkozy.
و إن كان فرانسوا هولاند مثل ساركوزي.
They are not. They are human beings with different views
انهم ليسو متشابهين. انهم بشر بأفكار مختلفة
and different visions for the world.
و وجهات نظر مختلفة نحو العالم.
When people say nothing can change,
عندما يقول الناس انه لا يمكن لشيء أن يتغير،
just stop and think what the world was like
توقف و فكر، كيف كان العالم
10, 20, 50, 100 years ago.
قبل 10 أو 20 أو 50 أو 100 عام مضت
Our world is defined by the pace of change.
عالمنا يعرّف برتم التغير.
We can all change the world.
يمكننا جميعاً أن نغير العالم
I gave you a very small example
أعطيتكم مثال صغير
of how one thing, the use of color,
كيف أن شيء واحد، استخدام الألوان
can make change happen.
باستطاعته إحداث تغيير
I want to make more change
أنا أريد أن أصنع المزيد من التغيير
as Prime Minister of my country,
كرئيس وزراء بلادي،
but every single one of you can make change happen
و لكن يمكن لأي واحد منكم أن يصنع تغييراً
if you want to.
إن أردتم ذلك.
President Roosevelt, he said,
الرئيس روزفلت، قال:
"Believe you can, and you are halfway there."
" آمن بأنك تستطيع، تكون قطعت نصف المشوار."
Efharisto and kalinihta.
شكرا و تصبحون على خير (باليونانية)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)